in this Baldur's Gate 3 Rogue class
guide I'm gonna be covering the Rogue
class including all three subclasses and
providing you some useful information
I'll be doing more build guides for
Baldur's Gate 3 for rogue but for now
let's take a look at how the Rogue
functions and its basics
Rogues are Savvy individuals that use
hit and run tactics to exploit enemy
weak spots increasing their damage when
their opponent is most vulnerable using
their sneak attack class feature and
although Rogues don't gain an extra
attack like many martial classes they
can still crank out quite a bit of
damage because of this Rogues Excel
outside of combat though and gain more
skills than just about any other class
except for Barts they also gain
expertise and many of them allowing them
to master many skill checks in the game
you'll usually find Rogues handling the
lock picking trapped disarming and
pickpocketing for a party but they can
also excel at dialogue with a little
charisma stealth is a huge part of
playing a rogue since sneak attack can
be easily triggered when hidden and
Arcane tricksters can cast their spells
more effectively when hidden at later
levels
next we'll take a look at how to set up
your Rogue during character creation for
best results we'll begin with abilities
first since this is arguably the most
important part aside from choosing your
subclass
your primary ability as a rogue is
dexterity with other abilities taking a
back seat and depending on what you
really want to do with your row you
could take Charisma for dialogue for
instance or intelligence if you plan to
become an Arcane trickster or just want
to be good at intelligent skill checks
wisdom is also not bad for perception
checks since Rogues typically check for
traps but you'll absolutely want some
Constitution regardless to increase your
HP dexterity increases your attack rolls
damage rolls boost Armor class
initiative and improve sleight of hand
acrobatics and stealth checks as well as
improves dexterity saving throws it's
incredibly good for Rogues
Constitution is there to help keep you
alive via HP since Rogues don't have a
huge Health pool and can help prevent
you from getting downed quickly
for these reasons I strongly recommend
that you invest at least 16 in dexterity
and 14 in Constitution during character
creation what you do after that depends
on what you're going for as I mentioned
but I'll give you some examples on what
you could do you can see on the screen
three different stat layouts based on
the type of Rogue that you want to play
note that I've changed these from the
recommendations as it's more optimized
for your character during the early
goings of the game
next we move to races yet Yankee
provides the Rogue with medium armor
proficiency they wouldn't otherwise get
as well as astral knowledge allowing
them to gain Proficiency in the skills
of one ability each long rest which is
great if you want to have nearly all
skills covered they will also gain Misty
Step at level 5 which can help with
Rogue positioning elf is good for
Longboat proficiency as well as Fey
ancestry they also gain dark vision
which can help land your attacks in Dark
Places High Elves also have perception
proficiency while wood elves have
stealth proficiency and can move further
either are a good choice granting one
skill proficiency you would likely take
anyway
deep gnome is also fantastic for
Advantage on wisdom intelligence and
Charisma saving throws as well as
Superior dark vision and they also have
advantage on stealth checks right if you
really want to be a sneaky Rogue
Lightfoot halflings are another solid
choice because they re-roll if they roll
a 1 on any attack roll ability check or
saving throw all but preventing them
from ever critically missing they can
also not be frightened easily and they
too have advantage on stealth checks
for skills what you select will largely
depend on the needs of your group and
whether or not you're handling dialogue
however all Rogue should probably at
least have sleight of hand stealth and
perception if possible this will allow
them to lock pick spot and disarm traps
and spot hidden objects and doors
next let's move to the character
progression of Rogues
at level 1 all Rogues gain the sneak
attack class feature which allows them
to add 1d6 damage to their melee
arranged attacks per odd level of Rogue
taken this means at level 3 Rogue this
will become 2d6 and at level 5 Rogue it
will become 3d6 and so on
however there are some stipulations to
trigger sneak attack and the first is
that if you want to sneak attack with a
melee weapon you must use a finesse
weapon finesse weapons are melee weapons
that can use dexterity for their attack
and damage roles instead of the default
strength stat and are usually rapiers
short swords scimitars and daggers
next is that your target must be
standing near a friendly character or
you must have advantage on your attack
against the target
there are different ways to gain
Advantage as a rogue and bg3 as they are
as follows cutting action hide this
allows the Rogue to hide using their
bonus action and gain sneak attack
damage with their action since you will
always have advantage against targets
that cannot see you this is more useful
for range snake attacks since it's
harder to make it into melee range and
remain hidden while in combat
assassinate initiative assassins
automatically gain Advantage when
attacking enemies who have not taken one
turn in combat yet this is useful for
gaining sneak attack on the first turn
only and is only applicable to the
Assassin subclass
flourish this weapon action does minimal
damage but sets the Target off balance
as a bonus action any attack made
against an off-balance character has
advantage
this allows you to then use your regular
attack with Advantage triggering sneak
attack this is only a once per short
rest bonus action though so you can't
use it every turn
prone attacking enemies that are prone
with a melee attack provides the
attacker Advantage allowing Rogues to
gain sneak attack damage with their
melee attacks
hold or paralyze some spells in bg3 like
hold person hold a character in place
and melee attacks made against these
targets always critical hit as well as
deal sneak attack damage make sure your
Mage has this if you're playing a rogue
[Music]
web this spell Roots an enemy in place
and attacks against them have advantage
[Music]
and snerd attacking enemies that are
ensnared also provides advantage
[Music]
sleep attacking enemies that are asleep
provides advantage and guarantees a
critical hit
[Music]
foreign
attacking blinded enemies also provides
advantage on attacks against them
and finally the lucky feat this can be
used to Grant advantage on attack rolls
three times for long rest
the two easiest ways are of course
attacking an enemy near a character or
using cutting action hide to go hidden
and then attack from ranged but you can
use this information to help plan your
attacks
make sure that you set up sneak attack
to ask under your reactions so that you
can attack with any ranged or melee
attack action and are still prompted for
sneak attack damage when it applies this
can prevent you from missing sneak
attack damage or prevent you from
applying it when it would be Overkill
since you can only gain sneak attack
damage once per route another tip is
that you should get in the habit of
pressing the shift key before using
cutting action hide while in combat so
you can move out of an enemy's cone of
vision before hiding if you can saving
you from having to pass a stealth check
to become hidden Rogues will also gain
expertise at this level doubling their
proficiency bonus in two skills they are
proficient in stealth's flight of hand
or perception are all good choices but
persuasion or deception are also not bad
if you went the dialogue route at level
2 Rogues gained cutting action allowing
them to use disengage Dash and hide as
bonus actions instead of actions which
means they can use one of these and
still attack on the same turn do not
underestimate how powerful this is and
taking advantage of this feature is a
big part of playing a rogue note that
these have separate icons on your action
bar from the original disengage Dash and
hide so make sure you're using the
correct ones
at level 3 Rogues will get to choose a
subclass from Thief assassin and Arcane
trickster and immediately gain a
subclass feature from their choice and
will go into these more in the subclass
section
a level 4 Rogues will gain their first
feat ability Improvement is good here
for more dexterity which will further
improve attack rolls damage rules Armor
class initiative sleight of hand
acrobatics and stealth checks as well as
improving dexterity saving throws
however there are some good ones to pick
here as well such as dual wielder if you
want to use two rapiers in game plus one
armor class lucky is great for picking
up some uses of advantage and
controlling outcomes and Sharpshooter is
great for boosting range damage
at level 5 ropes can use the reaction to
reduce the damage they take from an
attack by half once per round at level 6
Rogues gain expertise in two more skills
they're proficient with doubling their
proficiency bonus in those skills at
level 7 Rogues that save against spells
or effects that Target their dexterity
take no damage even if the speller
effect would normally deal half should
they say and they only take half damage
if they fail drastically reducing the
average damage they take from these
effects at level 8 Rogues will gain
their second feat ability Improvement is
still good here for dexterity or you can
pick up any of the other ones like dual
wielder lucky or sharpshooter at level 9
Rogues gain their final subclass feature
and as mentioned before we'll get into
those in the subclass section in just a
minute
at level 10 Rogues will gain their third
feat and this is an extra feat that no
other class besides fighter gets ability
Improvement is still good here for
dexterity if it's not 20 yet or you can
pick up any of the other ones like dual
wielder lucky or sharpshooter
at level 11 Rogues cannot roll below a
10 when making an ability check with a
skill they're proficient with this
nearly guarantees they will pass any
ability checks they make since they'll
have Plus 8 from expertise and 4 skills
and that doesn't include their ability
modifiers or other bonuses this is also
exceptionally good for stealthy gameplay
as it's much easier to stay hidden at
level 12 Rogues will gain their final
feat you should have 20 dexterity by
this point so choose any of the other
Feats I suggested
next we'll take a look at Rogue
equipment Rogues and bg3 have light
armor proficiency by default which works
well since they have high dexterity that
will then be applied to their Armor
class medium armor is also fine if you
gain proficiency from a race or
multi-class but make sure it doesn't
have disadvantage on stealth checks
weapon wise the road could really
benefit from a few ranged weapon
proficiencies like heavy crossbow or
Longbow that are typically found under
Marshall weapons but otherwise they
pretty much got what they need covered
they have Rapier and short sword
proficiency as well as simple weapons so
they'll likely use a short bow and rape
your short sword or pair of short swords
if no other proficiencies are required
via race or multi-class they need to use
a finesse melee weapon for sneak attack
so their options are somewhat limited
anyway
accessorywise look for things that boost
their Armor class to help them stay
alive or stealth since the easier it is
to hide the easier it is to sneak attack
choosing a rogue subclass in bg3 comes
down to a few factors do you plan to
Ambush enemies outside of combat
regularly from stealth do you want to be
able to cast some spells that might come
in handy both inside and outside of
combat and do you want to have more
capability once combat has been
triggered
if you plan to Ambush enemies outside of
combat often assassin is the way to go
you gain guaranteed critical hits when
the hitting surprised enemies and you'll
regain both your action and bonus action
even if you just use them before combat
triggered normally if you use an action
before you begin combat you won't gain
another one before your next turn but
assassins do
if you want some spell casting Arcane
trickster is the way to go and they can
use their spells to help sneak through
areas effectively as well as put enemies
to sleep for devastating criticals Thief
is fantastic once combat has begun since
they gain an extra bonus action which
they can use for a variety of things and
you'll often find many other classes
will dip three levels in a thief just to
pick this up
all Rogues gain their first subclass
feature at level 3 when they select
their subclass and then once again at
level 9. these features are not the only
thing that separates these subclasses
however since Arcane tricksters also
gain spell casting while thief and
assassin do not
let's take a look at assassins first at
level 3 assassins gain assassinate
initiative which allows them to have
advantage in combat against enemies that
haven't yet taken their turn this means
they are almost always going to land
their first attack in combat and this
attack will be able to deal sneak attack
damage without having to do anything
they also deal critical damage when
successfully attacking surprise to
enemies surprised enemies are usually
enemies you've attacked from out of
combat that had no idea they are about
to be attacked are not already in combat
and they could not see you this is
relatively easy to pull off if you know
where the enemies are going to be
also at level 3 assassins will always
have their action and bonus action when
combat begins this is very useful
because usually if you perform an action
or bonus action just before triggering
combat you will not have these when
combat starts this allows them to get
the jump on enemies outside of combat
and then attack once again usually
immediately effectively giving them two
attacks if they do this before they
trigger combat at level 9 assassins can
adopt a new appearance that lets them
change their race and gender until long
rest or until they cancel it this is a
ritual action that can be used as many
times per day as they want outside of
combat as far as I can tell it doesn't
operate much differently than disguise
self
it causes the game and characters inside
it to view you as a different character
which allows you to Rob cheat steal and
then end your disguise with your
reputation intact
usually guards in the game will be
looking for you but if you used
infiltration expertise when doing these
things they will be looking for the
wrong person
secondly if you do murder someone you
can end your infiltration expertise and
you speak with the dead on them
successfully usually people don't want
to speak with their Killers so when you
speak to them as yourself after you end
your disguise then you'll be able to
thirdly it can change dialogue
encounters completely though I don't
have a complete list of all the possible
changes
and fourthly you can use infiltration
expertise to meet the criteria for
certain equipment that gives benefits
When a particular race uses them this
comes in handy if you find an item you
really like but you're not the correct
race for the extra benefit
note that using infiltration expertise
will not change your racial features
now let's take a look at Thief
at level 3 thieves gain fast hands
granting them a second bonus action in
combat this allows them to attack a
second time with their offhand use
cutting action to disengage hide or Dash
twice or they can jump and still do one
of these things and attack in the same
turn there is a ton of application for
this especially multi-class with other
classes that have strong bonus actions
but we'll get into that more in the
multi-class section
also at this level thieves gain
resistance to fall damage cutting this
in half this is good for when they jump
down from high places or when they get
flung off a cliff by an effect or a
spell and can often save their life
at level 9 thieves can turn invisible
whenever they want as an action once
every short rest invisibility ends early
if you attack casts another spell take
an action or take damage however this is
quite useful for getting past heavily
guarded places should you want to avoid
combat
and this brings us to Arcane Trickster
at level 3 Arcane tricksters will gain
spell casting and be able to cast some
spells from a limited spell list as well
as select some from The Wizard spell
list they use intelligence for their
spell casting when using these spells
but they don't have to prepare them like
Wizards also at this level Arcane
tricksters gained Mage Handler gertamine
this lets them summon a magehand that
can interact with objects taking or
stowing items and pickpocketing and
disarming traps Andy for thieves from
safe distances
however this is currently not working in
bg3 severely limiting the usefulness of
this subclass feature at level 9 enemies
have disadvantage against your hostile
spells when casting them while you're
hidden this almost ensures they connect
but the issue is that Arcane tricksters
only know up to level 2 spells and only
have two level 2 spell slots in pg3
meaning you won't get much mileage out
of this subclass feature
and that brings us to multi-classing in
this section of our guide we'll take a
look at multi-classing a rogue in bg3
and what other classes you might
multi-class with keep in mind this is
not a complete list but rather helpful
suggestions that make good pairings
Rogues are heavily front loaded meaning
they gain cutting action at level 2 and
they gain a lot from their subclass
features at level 3. this means the
first most likely place you would
multi-class a rogue would be after this
point from this point onward it's a lot
less cut and dry about when you should
multi-class as it really depends on what
you need out of Rogue the level 9
subclass features are underwhelming for
the most part so going to level 9 is
less important than it would be if these
were stronger
could probably make the best case for
thief if you really need the
invisibility or Arcane trickster if you
plan to multi-class with wizard to pick
up more spell slots be able to learn
level 3 spells from Scrolls and be able
to upcast lower level spells
when it comes to multi-classing Assassin
I like three levels of assassin with
nine levels of fighter this allows you
to gain a fighting style and extra feet
medium armor proficiency as well as
extra attack Fighters also gain
indomitable at level 9 allowing them to
re-roll failed saves once
three assassin and nine gloomstalker is
also a great pairing in order to deal
increased damage on your first attack in
combat which is also a free attack
provide you with extra attack and grants
a fighting style as well
when it comes to multi-classic Arcane
trickster I like nine Arcane trickster
and three wizard which will give you
access to level 3 spell slots and
provide you with many more spell slots
than you normally have Wizards can also
learn spells from Scrolls so you could
still learn level 3 spells this way as
well picking up Fireball and lightning
bolt among others this will let you cast
these with enemies having disadvantage
on saving throws if you do so while
hidden
when it comes to multi-classing Thief
three thief and 9 sorcer gives you two
bonus actions they can use to cast
Quicken spells on top of their other
spell they can cast with irregular
action this also gives Sorcerers light
armor proficiency and some better skills
along with cutting action in case they
need to disengage from a bad situation
three thief and nine fighter or nine
Ranger allows you to dual wield
effectively with the extra attacks these
classes gain this would allow the thief
to contribute another offhand attack on
the extra attack essentially getting 4
hits per turn and providing these
classes with cutting action boosting
their Mobility
three thief and 9 War domain allows
clerics to make an attack with their
action and twice with their bonus action
in one turn which can be huge damage if
they are set up properly
so that wraps up our road guide I hope
you guys found this informative and
helpful and as always if you have other
tips for other players please leave them
in the comments below and if you have
questions leave them there as well and I
will try and answer them as soon as I
can
[Music]